
<body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:e="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns">
   <p>This reference document describes the European Literary Text
      Collection (ELTeC), a major deliverable of COST Action 16204, <title>Distant
         Reading</title>. The ELTeC is a principled collection of literary text corpora, uniformly
      encoded in TEI XML, and representing
      the production of novels in different European languages for the period 1840 to 1920. The
      present document begins with a description of 
      the principles and sampling methods used to construct the collection, and is followed by
      detailed
      technical documentation of the TEI XML schema used to encode the textual components and the
      metadata of the
      collection.  All texts included in the ELTeC conform to the schema
      described by this document. </p>
 <div><head>Corpus Design</head> <div>
         <head>Principles and sampling method</head>
        <!-- <p>The task for WG1 is to develop guidelines for data and metadata for the creation of the
            ELTeC. This task can be split up into several distinct tasks: Guidelines for corpus
            design, basic annotation and metadata schemes and workflow. This discussion paper
            focuses on corpus design and metadata because both tasks interplay with each other.</p>-->
         <p>The goal of CA16204 is to create a <!--big--> benchmark corpus of literature from 1840-1920
            <!--(first period) --> adequate to the needs of many different computational distant reading methods for corpus annotation
            and analysis. <!--The task of creating annotation guidelines of WG1 needs to be closely
            communicated and coordinated with WG2 in order to know which methods and tools needs
            which kind(s) of annotation model and format. The same holds for the development of the
            metadata scheme.--> <!--</p>
         <p>For creating such a benchmark corpus, we need a--> The corpus design should support
            comparison of texts and individual sub-collections selected according to the metadata
            associated with each text.  
         It should be possible to sample sub-collections
            from the ELTeC for specific tasks and research questions. In a first step, we focus on
            the development of clear, operationalized, transparent and motivated selection criteria
            for the corpus.</p>
         <p>It is important to stress that we do not intend to define what a novel is by defining
            what kind of selection criteria we will use for ELTeC. The category novel may be divided
            into three groups where at least one of the following core criteria is met: a) textual:
            length (>10.000 words), prose, fiction, narrative structure b) paratextual (the term
            ‘novel’ or  equivalent appears in the title or subtitle of the text) and c) contextual:
            the text is bibliographically listed with the UDC: 82-31 Novels. Full-length
            stories.</p>
     
   <!--      <head>Method</head>
   -->      <p>We follow a non-normative but metadata-based approach of sampling criteria which will
            follow a corpus design approach. Corpus sampling criteria are mostly oriented/developed
            by the research question or/and contexts of the corpus creators group. In CA16204, we
            have neither only a single research question nor a fixed and previously known corpus
            creator group. The research context of the Action is more interested in knowledge
            production in a methodological sense and does not prefer a single method, model or
            theory. Furthermore, the member group of the Action will fluctuate and consist of
            researches from different disciplines with different theoretical and cultural contexts.
            Thus, we need to build the corpus design on a methodical basis. With this method, we
            will also be able to select canonical texts as well but not exclusively. </p>
         <p> Representativeness is a kind of ideal which we would like to pursue but which cannot be
            achieved as whole. We will therefore aim to represent the variety of a population. In
            line with the MoU, the ELTeC will be designed as a monitor corpus where texts (from
            different languages and periods) can be added over time. We then need to decide which
            criterion is balanced in which way and interplays with other criteria.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>Requirements of sampling criteria</head>
         <p>According to the MoU, the corpus design should be balanced with respect to language and
            publication date of the texts. This means that the corpus should not be based solely on
            chronological criteria, meaning that we need a text from each year of the period in
            question. The main sampling criterion ‘language’ will require not to include
            translations at all. We will prefer to take the first edition of a novel or editions of
            these novels. By a novel, we prefer to take the edition of the book, hence we don't
            prefer novels only printed in periodicals, unless a particular literary tradition only
            features novels printed in serial format. If we consider editions of a novel, these
            editions should be freely available (free licences for reusing them. The first edition
            is more interesting from a philological point of view. It represents the authentic texts
            of the authors. Dealing with historical texts might require some cleaning up or
            normalizations. We will merge all word forms which are separated by line breaks. At the
            moment, we must assume that there are no (sufficiently good) normalization tools for
            every language. Later editions of a novel may be already normalized in some way. This
            might lead to different text representations in ELTeC which should be indicated in the
            metadata. </p>
         <p>Considering also later freely available editions of a novel has two advantages: First,
            members of the Action already can provide machine-readable text documents (html, TEI
            etc.) of later editions and second, in some languages it might be easier to find later
            editions which already exist in a machine-readable format (in this way we do not have to
            put effort in digitizing them).</p>
         <p> Electronically availability should not be a leading sampling criterion although
            availability is a limiting factor. A text should not be excluded from ELTeC because it
            is not digitized, but it should be excluded if the text cannot be made freely available
            in ELTeC. If we only use availability as a selecting criterion, we are at risk of
            copying projects such as ‘Gutenberg’ for example. The issue remains of finding
            additional funds to digitise non-canonical books. Un til that moment, the solution would
            be to create pilot corpora (that can later be supplemented or substituted by an alterna
            tive) for literatures that do not have a significant number of digitized texts. </p>
         <p> We then need additional criteria which can be applied without having to know (read) the
            texts in question. The criteria should be checked without a deep knowledge about the
            texts. Otherwise, this will oppose the goal of the whole Action and the methodical
            approach of distant reading. The criteria should be operationalizable, meaning decidable
            from text metadata. Here, we define text metadata in a wider scope than only the
            classical bibliographical metadata. In this way corpus design interacts with metadata.
            Some of the text’s metadata can be used as sampling criteria. These criteria are
            text-external and -internal criteria (cf. Hunston 2008) on which we then need to rely.
            The selection criteria may be assisted by bibliographical overviews (wherever available)
            for each language in order to avoid possible canon-derived bias. </p>
         <p>We suggest using an online table as a means of collecting nominations for inclusion in
            the ELTeC but other methods are feasible. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head> Sampling criteria </head>
         <p>For creating a language collection two steps have to be done: First step is selection:
            identifying text candidates. Second step is balancing: proportion within the corpus.
            Both steps are defined in this document.</p>
         <p>Principles:</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>We will represent the variety of production and aim to maximize the variety within
               each time period.</item>
            <item>We will prefer to collect novels published as a book in first as well as later
               editions over novels published in serial publications (journals).</item>
            <item>We will not include translations.</item>
            <item>We will consider only freely available texts and trying to reuse already digitized
               texts.</item>
            <item>We will use non-normative sampling criteria which allow for selecting canonical
               novels and non-canonical novels.</item>
            <item>Metadata should indicate the type of text representation (normalized or
               non-normalized, first or later editions etc.). </item>
            <item>We will strictly follow the selection and balancing criteria and we prefer 80
               novels meeting these criteria over 100 novels which do not meet the criteria.</item>
         </list>
         <p>Organization</p>
         <list>
            <item>Please note: Contact the sampling support Team: Carolin, Lou, Pieter and Diana!
               Task: To control the corpus sampling according to the selection criteria. </item>
         </list>
         <p>Criteria: Eligibility. </p>
         <p> In order to be included (selection), a text must... </p>
         <list>
            <item>have been first published as a book (or or in case of need as series publication)
               between 1840 and 1920, sub-grouped and equally split by decades, </item>
            <item>have first been published in a European country. [maybe not "first": within that
               decade],</item>
            <item>be a novel, i.e. a fictional prose narrative,</item>
            <item>have originally been written in the language of the given subcollection.</item>
         </list>
         <p>Criteria: Composition. </p>
         <p>Among the novels in each language the subcollection must contain... </p>
         <list>
            <item>at least 10%-50% have been written by female authors for the language
               subcollection.</item>
            <item>9 to 11 authors are represented with exact three novels.</item>
            <item>at least 30% are highly canonical novels and at least 30% should be novels of low canonicity;
 canonicity is assessed by investigating the number of times a title was reprinted during the period 1970-2009.
               </item>
            <item>at least 20% are short novels (10-50k word tokens), at least 20% are long novels
               (>200k word tokens).</item>
         </list>
         <list type="gloss">

            <label> Date : 1840 to 1920 (first iteration)</label>
            <item>
               <p>We will divide into four groups</p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item>group A (1840-1859): code T1</item>
                  <item>group B (1860-1879): code T2</item>
                  <item>group C (1880-1899): code T3</item>
                  <item>group D (1900-1920): code T4</item>
               </list>
            </item>

            <label>Language of the text</label>
            <item><p>The MoU defines the languages to be sampled. It does not propose distinguishing
                  regional variation (e.g. in German), nor geographical variation (e.g. the French
                  spoken in Belgium, France, or Switzerland). It assumes only European varieties, so
                  English excludes US English; French excludes Quebecois. </p>
               <p> We follow a language-based approach (not country-based). This means for example
                  that we include Swiss German texts in the German language collection. We prefer
                  standard varieties over dialect varieties if sampling criteria for text candidates
                  are met. </p>
            </item>
            <label>Reprint count</label>
            <item><p>We propose to use the number of times a work is reprinted as an objective
                  measure of its reception during the period 1970-2009, using categories like the following: </p><list>
                  <item>low: few or no reprints found during this period,</item>
                  <item>high: many reprints found during this period</item>
                  <item>Note that the reprint count does not include digitizations of texts.</item>
               </list></item>
            <label>Author gender</label>
            <item>
               <p>We use the following three categories for actual (not claimed) author gender </p><list>
                  <item>male</item>
                  <item>female</item>
                  <item>mixed (more than one author)</item>
                  <item>undefined</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <label>Length</label>
            <item>
               <p>We include a variety of lengths</p>
               <list>
                  <item>short (10k-50k word tokens) </item>
                  <item>medium (50k-100k word tokens)</item>
                  <item>long (>100k word tokens)</item>
               </list></item>
         </list>
      </div></div>
   <div><head>Corpus Encoding</head>
   <div>
      <head>Encoding Principles</head>
      <p>The MoU for the project notes that <q>Distant Reading methods cover a wide range of
         computational methods for literary text analysis, such as authorship attribution, topic
         modelling, character network analysis, or stylistic analysis.</q> The focus of the ELTeC
         encoding scheme is therefore not to represent texts in all their original complexity of
         structure or appearance, but rather to facilitate a richer and better-informed distant
         reading than a transcription of lexical content alone would permit. In designing this
         encoding scheme, we have applied the following principles: <list>
            <item>There should be a guaranteed minimum level of encoding for all texts in the
               ELTeC.</item>
            <item>The encoding should reflect the analytic needs of <soCalled>distant
               reading</soCalled>, rather than those of the digital editor.</item>
            <item>At the same time, the encoding should not misrepresent the text as originally
               created and received.</item>
            <item>The encoding must be easy to apply in a consistent way, starting from both basic
               OCR and pre-existing digital versions.</item>
         </list> The goal is not to duplicate the work of scholarly editors or to produce (yet
         another) digital edition of a specific source document. Rather it is to ensure that the
         ELTeC texts can be processed satisfactorily, even by simple minded (but XML-aware) systems
         primarily concerned with lexis, and to make life easier for the developers of such systems. </p>
      
      <p>In selecting features for inclusion in the markup scheme, we have been guided, but not
         limited, by existing practice as far as possible. Our main goal has been to identify a
         small core set of textual features which can be readily (preferably automatically)
         identified in existing digital transcriptions, or easily and consistently provided by new
         transcriptions. </p>
      
      <p>We distinguish three <soCalled>levels</soCalled> of encoding, referred to below as level
         zero, level one and level two. All ELTeC texts are made available at level zero, the basic
         encoding format. Some texts may additionally be made available at levels one or two, which
         provide a richer set of encoded features. For example: a level one text will include
         semantic information missing from a level zero text; a level two text will include
         tokenization information missing from a level one text. As far as possible conversion
         between levels will be automatically scripted, but this is not possible in the general
         case. </p>
      <p>This document lists all the textual features which are to be distinguished in an ELTeC
         conformant transcription at one of these three levels. Whenever a given feature exists in a
         text, it will be marked up as indicated here. No other features will be captured by the
         markup: if some textual feature not provided for here is identified by a marked up source
         text, that markup will be removed (though it may be retained in a version of the text
         encoded at a different level). </p>
      
      <p>All ELTeC documents are TEI conformant, and therefore include a TEI Header, as discussed in
         section <ptr target="#hdr"/> below.</p>
   </div>
   
   
   <div>
      <head>Basic Transcription Guidelines (all levels) </head>
      <p>The basic unit of the ELTeC collection is a single novel, represented by a single
            <gi>TEI</gi> element, consisting of a <gi>teiHeader</gi> element containing metadata
         specific to that novel and a <gi>text</gi> element containing a normalised transcription of
         the text itself. We propose no mechanism (other than metadata) to encode units larger than
         a single novel, such as multipart novel series like Proust's <title>A la recherche du temps
            perdu</title> or Balzac's <title>Les Rougon-Macquart</title>. Each text should be
         transcribed in full from a specific identifiable edition, typically the first, and the
         source documented in the TEI Header. The original spelling and punctuation of the source
         should be retained, but details of typography are not required: hence words hyphenated
         across line or page breaks should be silently reassembled. </p>
      <!-- page breaks-->
      <p>To facilitate checking of a transcription against its source during production, the
            <gi>pb</gi> element may be used to mark the point in a transcription where a new
         page begins in the source. An identifier for each <gi>pb</gi> element may be provided in a
         level 1 text to facilitate linkage to a page image of the corresponding source page. This
         element is
         not required in a level 0 text. </p>
      <p>Running titles, page footers, catchwords and other forms of printed paratext are all
         omitted from an ELTeC transcription, with the exception of a page number, which may be
         supplied as value of the <att>n</att> attribute. Note that this attribute supplies the page
         number as specified by the source. If no page number is given, the value should be enclosed
         in brackets. </p>
      <p> If a page begins with the second part of a hyphenated word, the <gi>pb</gi> tag may appear
         after that word in order to simplify lexical processing. Otherwise its position should be
         the same in transcription and source. </p>
      <!-- liminal material -->
      <p>As well as a titlepage or a table of contents, a published novel often includes material
         such as forewords or appendixes additional to the text of the novel itself. This
            <term>liminal</term> matter is included in an ELTeC text only if it is believed to be
         authorial. Material before the body of the text begins is collected within a <gi>front</gi>
         element, and material following the body in a <gi>back</gi> element. In either case,
         distinct sections of the material, if encoded, are represented by a <gi>div</gi> with its
            <att>type</att> attribute set to <code>liminal</code>.</p>
      <p>At level zero, titlepages and tables of contents are omitted. At level one, they are
         replaced by a <gi>gap</gi> element. Non-authorial liminal material is silently omitted at
         all levels. </p>
      <!-- body divisions -->
      <p>Within the body of a text, major structural divisions (parts, sections, chapters etc.) will
         be captured using the generic <gi>div</gi> element, with attributes <att>type</att>,
            <att>xml:lang</att>, <att>xml:id</att> and <att>n</att> used as further detailed
         below.</p>
      <p>The names used for hierarchic structural divisions of a novel above the chapter are
         arbitrary, culture-specific, and often inconsistent : in some novels things called
            <q>part</q> contain things called <q>book</q> and in others the reverse. We propose to
         follow TEI in using a single element (<gi>div</gi>) for every hierarchical structural
         division, down to the level of <q>chapter</q>.</p>
      <p>The <att>type</att> attribute is used to indicate the function of a structural division. It
         should have one of the following values: <list type="gloss">
            <label>liminal</label>
            <item>authorial preface, foreword, back matter, etc.</item>
            <label>titlepage</label>
            <item>(within front or back) contains title page text: level 1 only</item>
            <label>notes</label>
            <item>(within front or back) contains authorial notes : level 1 only</item>
            <label>part</label>
            <item>any structural subdivision of a text larger than a chapter e.g. part, volume
               etc.</item>
            <label>chapter</label>
            <item>smallest structural subdivision of the body of a text</item>
         </list></p>
      <p>A short novel may have no subdivision at all, in which case the <gi>div</gi> element should
         not be used. No further subdivisions within a <tag>div type='chapter'</tag> are permitted.
         If the text of a chapter is subdivided in some way, for example by means of a number, a row
         of stars, a horizontal rule, or similar device, this should be indicated in the markup by
         means of a <gi>milestone</gi> element. If a chapter contains an embedded text of some kind,
         for example a quoted letter or other narrative, this should be marked using the
            <gi>quote</gi> element. </p>
      <!--  <valList type="semi">
                     <valItem ident="liminal">
                    <desc>authorial preface, foreword, back matter etc.</desc>
                 </valItem>
                 <valItem ident="chapter">
                    <desc>chapter not further divided</desc>
                 </valItem>
                 <valItem ident="group">
                    <desc>any grouping of chapters or groups, e.g. part, volume,
                       etc.</desc>
                 </valItem><valItem ident="titlepage">
                    <desc>title page transcription (level 1 only)</desc>
                 </valItem>
        <valItem ident="notes">
                    <desc>authorial notes, collected within back  (level 1 only)</desc>
                 </valItem>
        
              </valList>-->
      <p>The (human) language in which a text is expressed is indicated explicitly by the
            <att>xml:lang</att> attribute which supplies the ISO 641-2 letter code for the language
         concerned. This attribute will always be supplied on the <gi>text</gi> element to specify a
         default, and may also appear on other elements to indicate passages where the language
         changes. The various different languages used in a given text will be itemized in its
         metadata (see <gi>langUsage</gi> element in the header). </p>
      <p>A single reference scheme will be defined for the whole corpus, with the following
         components: <list>
            <item>text identifier : every text will have an identifier consisting of its three
               letter language code in upper case and a five digit serial number, for example
                  <code>FRA00042</code></item>
            <item>chapter identifier: each chapter or equivalent will have an identifier
               concatenating the text identifier and a three digit serial number, for example
                  <code>FR042012</code> is the twelfth chapter of the 42nd French novel. </item>
            <item>If sub-chapter segmentation is implemented, then the segments will append a
               further four digit serial number.</item>
            <item>liminal divisions are not identified; the front element has an identifier
               concatenating the text identifier and the value 000; the back element has an
               identifier concatenating the text identifier and the value 999.</item>
         </list>The identifier will be supplied as the value of an <att>xml:id</att> attribute on
         each <gi>text</gi>, <gi>div</gi>, front, back, or <gi>s</gi> element as appropriate. Adding
         this identifier is an easily automated task built into the workflow for accession to the
         ELTeC.</p>
      <p>Note that these identifiers will not necessarily correspond with the numbering used in a
         particular source text. In a work where the first twelve chapters are considered to form
         part one, and the next twelve constitute part two, the first chapter of the second part
         will have an identifier ending <code>013</code>, even though it may be numbered
            <code>1</code> in a source text.</p>
      <p>We do not preserve the lineation of running prose in our source texts, since this is always
         purely an artefact of the source edition. For the same reason we reassemble words broken
         across a line break, silently removing any hyphen present. (This will make it impossible to
         use our texts for hyphenation studies. So be it.) </p>
      <p>The title of a chapter, or of any other subdivision, as given in the source should be
         encoded using the TEI <gi>head</gi> element. There may be more than one such element at the
         start of a <gi>div</gi> element. Novels occasionally include other initial matter, such as
         a quotation, or a summary of the content of the chapter; these are not specially treated in
         ELTeC texts. </p>
      <p>The chapters of a novel mostly consist of prose, arranged in paragraphs. It is not unusual
         to find other structures however, specifically verse, or passages of dialogue presented as
         if in a play, with speaker labels and even stage directions. Less frequently, novels may
         contain material presented in list or tabular formats. Graphics with their own associated
         heading or other text are also frequent. </p>
      <p>Novels are also full of direct speech, represented using various different conventions, but
         almost always distinguished from the narrative voice. The first person narrative is also
         common, but may be regarded as a special case. How exactly different narrative strands are
         articulated in a novel, and the extent to which they may be characterised by their lexis
         has been a preoccupation of many <q>distant reading</q> style analyses. Although it might
         be helpful to distinguish material purporting to be direct speech from material purporting
         to be narrative in our basic encoding, doing so consistently and accurately would be
         problematic. ELTeC texts therefore do no more than preserve existing punctuation. The
            <gi>p</gi> element is used for everything which is typeset as a separate block on the
         page, including both paragraphs and list items; the <gi>l </gi>element is used for verse
         lines or similar, typically set off from the rest of the text. Illustrations and any
         associated text such as a title or heading are excluded. Passages set as if in drama are
         not specially treated. </p>
      <p>Printed texts typically deploy a number of conventions which can cause problems for
         linguistic analyses of even the most basic kind. Changes of font or style (italicization or
         use of superscript, for example) usually signal something, which an analysis should take
         into account. However, determining the function of such typographic variation is not always
         straightforward. ELTeC texts (at level 0) therefore simply indicate the presence of
         typographic salience, using the <gi>hi</gi> element.</p>
   </div>
   <div>
      <head>Transcription Guidelines (level 1)</head>
      <p>ELTeC encoding at level zero aims above all for consistency and transparency in what is
         reliably achievable, leaving most problematic issues to be addressed by linguistic
         annotation. </p>
      <p>If however a text has been derived from a digital version in which a more ambitious range
         of textual features has already been captured, whether by means of TEI-style markup or
         styling information such as that provided by Word, or if there are sufficient resources
         available to provide a slightly reacher encoded version, a novel may be encoded at ELTeC
         level 1, using additional elements discussed in this section. Note that a level one text
         can always automatically be converted to a level zero text, if this is necessary for
         compatibility or for some other reason. (A script to do this is available <ref
            target="https://distantreading.github.io/Scripts/detagger.xsl">on the project
            website</ref>) The reverse conversion, from level zero to level one, requires human
         intervention. </p>
      <p>At level 1, the element <gi>gap</gi> should be used to indicate when something has been
         omitted from the encoding. For example, a suppressed graphic, or foreword, which at level
         zero are silently omitted, should be represented at level 1 by an explicit <gi>gap</gi>
         element, with attributes indicating what has been omitted from the encoding.</p>
      <p>At level 1, the following additional elements can be used to mark up the significance of
         some stretch of text which would otherwise simply be marked as typographically salient
         using <gi>hi</gi>: <list>
            <label><gi>foreign</gi></label>
            <item>a word or phrase in a foreign language</item>
            <label>
               <gi>title</gi></label>
            <item>the title of a book, piece of music, etc.</item>
            <label>
               <gi>label</gi></label>
            <item>any form of heading or label found within a paragraph of text</item>
            <label><gi>emph</gi></label>
            <item>a word or phrase being linguistically emphasized e.g. by being shouted</item>
         </list> The <gi>hi</gi> is also sometimes used for indications of superscript characters
         (such as French <soCalled>14&#x1d49;</soCalled>); these should simply be removed.
         <!--Instead, the TEI element
                        <gi>abbr</gi> should be used to indicate the presence of an abbreviated
                     word: <code><gi>abbr</gi>14e&lt;/abbr></code>-->
      </p>
      <p>When a sequence of verse lines, or a passage from some other narrative level such as a
         letter is quoted within a text, the <gi>l</gi> or <gi>p</gi> elements representing it
         should be wrapped in the <gi>quote</gi> element made available by the ELTeC level one
         schema.</p>
      <p>It is not unusual to find special devices such as a row of stars or a rule in the middle of
         a chapter, usually indicating a discontinuity in the narrative timeline, or structural
         shift. Such indications may be simply ignored in an ELTeC level zero text; at level 1, the special
         purpose <gi>milestone</gi> element may be used to mark their presence.</p>
      <p>Level 1 texts may also represent authorial notes, if these are present, using the element
            <gi>note</gi> to contain the body of the note, and the element <gi>ref</gi> to represent
         the point of attachment for the note. Wherever they appear in the text, notes are always
         separated from it and encoded in a separate <gi>div</gi> element within the <gi>back</gi>
         element. See examples. </p>
      <p>Occasionally, the text being transcribed contains self-evident errors. Where these are
         caused by the encoding process (e.g. an OCR error), these are always silently corrected in
         the transcription. Where however the original itself is faulty, however, and the
         transcriber (or a textual editor) has corrected it, the correction should be signalled by
         using the <gi>corr</gi> element available at level one. </p>
   </div><div><head>Transcription Guidelines (level 2)</head>
      <p>At ELTeC level2, all existing elements are retained and two new elements <gi>s</gi>
         and <gi>w</gi> are introduced to support segmentation of running text into sentence-like
         and word-like sequences respectively. Individual
         tokens are marked using the <gi>w</gi> element, and decorated with one or more of the
         TEI-defined linguistic attributes <att>pos</att>, <att>lemma</att>, and
         <att>join</att>. Both words and punctuation marks are considered to be
         <soCalled>tokens</soCalled> in this sense, although the TEI suggests
         distinguishing the two cases using <gi>w</gi> and <gi>pc</gi> respectively.
         The
         <gi>s</gi> (segment) element is used to provide an end-to-end tessellating
         segmentation of the whole sequence of <gi>w</gi> elements, based on orthographic
         form. This provides a convenient extension of the existing text-body-div hierarchy
         within which tokens are located. The elements <gi>p</gi>, <gi>head</gi>, and
         <gi>l</gi> (which contain just text at levels 0 and 1) at level 2 can contain a
         sequence of <gi>s</gi> elements. Empty elements <gi>gap</gi>, <gi>milestone</gi>,
         <gi>pb</gi> or <gi>ref</gi> are also permitted within text content at any point,
         but these are disregarded when segmentation is carried out. Each <gi>s</gi> element
         can contain a sequence of <gi>w</gi> elements, either directly, or wrapped in one of
         the sub-paragraph elements <gi>corr</gi>, <gi>emph</gi>, <gi>foreign</gi>,
         <gi>hi</gi>, <gi>label</gi>, or <gi>title</gi>. To this list we  add the element
         <gi>rs</gi> (referring string), provided by the TEI for the encoding of any form
         of entity name, such as a Named Entity Recognition procedure might produce. </p>
      <p> This approach implies that <gi>w</gi> elements may appear at two levels in the
         hierarchy which may upset some software; it also implies that <gi>w</gi> elements
         must be properly contained within one of these elements, without overlap. <!--If either
         issue proves to be a major stumbling block, an alternative would be to remove the
         tags demarcating these sub-paragraph elements, indicating their semantics instead by
         additional attribute values on the <gi>w</gi> elements they contain.--> </p>
      <p>This TEI XML format is equally applicable to the production of training data for
         applications using machine learning techniques and to the outputs of such systems.
         However, since such machine learning applications typically operate on text content
         in a tabular format only, XSLT filters which transform (or generate) the XML markup
         discussed here from such tabular formats without loss of information are envisaged.
         At the time of writing, however, Working Group 2 has yet to put this proposed
         architecture to the test. </p></div>
   <div>

      <head>TEI Elements and textual features</head>
      <p>The following summary table lists the textual features which every ELTeC text must capture,
         together with an indication of how that feature should be represented. <table>
            <row role="label">
               <cell>Textual Feature</cell>
               <cell>Encoding</cell>
               <cell>Note</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Page break</cell>
               <cell><tag>pb/</tag></cell>
               <cell><att>n</att> attribute gives attested number of page; optional at level
                  0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Title page</cell>
               <cell><tag>div type="titlepage"</tag> within <gi>front</gi></cell>
               <cell>Optional at level 0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Authorial preface, foreword, appendix, etc</cell>
               <cell><tag>div type="liminal"</tag> within <gi>front</gi> or <gi>back</gi> as
                  appropriate</cell>
               <cell>Non-authorial matter is silently omitted</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>volume, chapter etc.</cell>
               <cell><gi>div</gi> nested as necessary within <gi>body</gi></cell>
               <cell><att>type</att> may be chapter, or group (for anything else); <att>n</att> may
                  indicate original numbering</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Heading or title</cell>
               <cell><gi>head</gi> at start of <gi>div</gi>; <gi>trailer</gi> at end</cell>
               <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Running title/page footer </cell>
               <cell>Omitted</cell>
               <cell>Page number only may be included in <gi>pb</gi></cell>
            </row>
           
            <row>
               <cell>Prose paragraph or list item</cell>
               <cell><gi>p</gi></cell>
               <cell>Discard any formatting information</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Verse line</cell>
               <cell><gi>l</gi></cell>
               <cell>Use only for verse lines in display blocks</cell>
            </row>


         </table></p>
      <p>Other textual features are treated differently at different encoding levels. They are
         listed in the following table: <table>
            <row role="label">
               <cell>Textual Feature</cell>
               <cell>Level 0 Encoding</cell>
               <cell>Level 1 Encoding</cell>
               <cell>Note</cell>
            </row>
            <!--    <row>
                        <cell>Title page</cell>
                        <cell>omitted</cell>
                        <cell><tag>div type="titlePage"</tag> within <gi>front</gi></cell>
                        <cell>omitted</cell>
                    </row>
           -->
            <row>
               <cell>Table of contents, errata list, other liminal matter</cell>
               <cell>omitted</cell>
               <cell><gi>gap</gi></cell>
               <cell>use <att>unit</att> and <att>quantity</att> to specify what has been
                  omitted</cell>
            </row>

            <row>
               <cell>Mid-chapter structural marker</cell>
               <cell>omitted</cell>
               <cell><tag>milestone/</tag></cell>
               <cell>use <att>unit</att>  and <att>type</att> to supply further detail</cell>
            </row>
            
            <row>
               <cell>Authorial footnote</cell>
               <cell>omitted</cell>
               <cell>transcribe text of note text within a <gi>note</gi> within <tag>div
                     type="notes"</tag> inside <gi>back</gi>; mark point of attachment with a
                     <gi>ref</gi></cell>
               <cell>use <att>target</att> on <gi>ref</gi> to point to <gi>note</gi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Font change</cell>
               <cell>Mark with <gi>hi</gi> (no attributes)</cell>
               <cell>Replace with <gi>foreign</gi>, <gi>title</gi>, <gi>label</gi>, <gi>emph</gi> as
                  appropriate</cell>

               <cell><!--Level 1 may use <att>rend</att> attribute with values ul ro sc it ?--> </cell>
            </row>

            <row>
               <cell>Graphic or illustration</cell>
               <cell>omitted</cell>
               <cell><tag>gap unit="graphic"</tag></cell>
               <cell><!--May use <att>desc</att> to describe the content of the graphic--></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Quotation or display block</cell>
               <cell><gi>p</gi> (or series of <gi>l</gi>)</cell>
               <cell><gi>quote</gi> containing one or more <gi>p</gi> or <gi>l</gi></cell>
               <cell>?</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Editorial correction</cell>
               <cell>unmarked</cell>
               <cell><gi>corr</gi></cell>
               <cell>Use when encoded text differs from printed original</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
      </p>


   </div>

</div><div><head>Corpus Metadata</head>

   <div xml:id="hdr">
      <head>Metadata in the TEI Header</head>

      <p>This section describes the metadata associated with each text (title, authorship, date
         etc.) and with the collection as a whole. The intention is to provide this in a
         standardised way to facilitate subsetting of the collection, using (for example) coded
         values for the descriptive selection criteria associated with the text. As far as possible,
         our text should represent the first complete printed edition of each novel selected. </p>
      <p>The TEI Header provides a very large number of possibilities for encoding such metadata. We
         will provide a checklist of the TEI Header elements which are always to be provided for
         each text, possibly in the form of a template. As in the body of the text, the intention is
         to provide a guaranteed minimal level of information, consistent across all parts of the
         ELTeC. </p>
      <p>Note that metadata may be supplied at (at least) two levels: the level of the ELTeC as a
         whole, and that of individual texts within it. Information which applies uniformly to all
         parts of the collection should be supplied in the ELTeC header; information specific to a
         particular document in the text header. </p>

      <p>Every ELTeC text includes a TEI Header supplying metadata to describe it. There is also a
         TEI Header for the whole collection, which has additional information common to all the
         texts. This section lists the header components which should be supplied for every text,
         indicating briefly specific usage rules. </p>

      <p>Here is the basic template for an individual ELTeC header: <egXML
            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <teiHeader type="novelHeader">
               <fileDesc>
                  <titleStmt>
                     <title><!-- title of work --></title>
                     <author><!-- information about the author --></author>
                     <respStmt><!-- information about the encoder --></respStmt>
                  </titleStmt>
                  <extent>
                     <!-- size of the text, in pages and words -->
                  </extent>
                  <publicationStmt>
                     <!-- standard text about status as part of ELTeC -->
                  </publicationStmt>
                  <sourceDesc>
                     <bibl>
                        <!-- bibliographic description of the printed source -->
                     </bibl>
                  </sourceDesc>
               </fileDesc>
               <profileDesc>
                  <!-- additional descriptive information, selection criteria, etc. -->
               </profileDesc>
               <revisionDesc>
                  <!-- revision information -->
               </revisionDesc>
            </teiHeader></egXML></p>
      <p> Each of the TEI elements shown above must be provided and used as described below. The
         ELTeC schemas will reject as invalid a document in which these conventions are not
         followed. </p>
      <p> The natural language used for text in the Header should be that of the language collection
         to which the text belongs, e.g. French if the text is in French. The attribute @xml:lang
         may be supplied on any element to indicate its content is in some other language where
         necessary. </p>
      <div>
         <head>The file description (<gi>fileDesc</gi>) </head>
         <div>
            <head>The title statement (<gi>titleStmt</gi>)</head>

            <p>This must supply : <list>
                  <item>at least one <gi>title</gi> element containing the standard title of the
                     work, followed by the phrase "ELTeC edition" (or its equivalent in the
                     appropriate language). Multiple title elements should be supplied only if the
                     title has been translated into some other language. </item>
                  <item>at least one <gi>author</gi> element containing the standard name of the
                     author, in the form SURNAME, FORENAMES (BIRTHYEAR - DEATHYEAR). If either date
                     is unknown, it should be replaced by a question-mark. The author name should be
                     that under which the author is conventionally catalogued, not necessarily that
                     found on the title page. </item>
                  <item>at least one <gi>respStmt</gi> element containing one or more <gi>name</gi>
                     elements and one or more <gi>resp</gi> elements indicating the person/s
                     responsible for producing the ELTeC edition, and the nature of their
                     responsibility respectively.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a simple example, for a German text : <egXML
                  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><titleStmt>
                     <title>Auf zwei Planeten : edizion ELTeC</title>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Two planets</title>
                     <author>Laßwitz, Kurd(1848-1910)</author>
                     <respStmt>
                        <resp>editor</resp>
                        <name>Alexander Geyken</name>
                     </respStmt>
                  </titleStmt></egXML>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The extent statement (<gi>extent</gi>)</head>

            <p>This must supply : <list>
                  <item>one or more <gi>measure</gi> elements, indicating the size of the text. The
                     size must be given as numeric content, and the type of measurement must be
                     either words or pages, as indicated by the @unit attribute. </item>
               </list> Here is a simple example, for a French text : </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><extent>
                  <measure unit="words">12000</measure>
                  <measure unit="pages">256</measure>
               </extent></egXML>
            <p>The page count may be derived from an external bibliographic source, and may not
               therefore correspond with the actual number of <gi>pb</gi> elements in the
               transcription. If no page count is available, no <tag>measure unit="pages"</tag>
               should be supplied. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The publication statement (<gi>publicationStmt</gi>)</head>
            <p>This must contain  a <gi>distributor</gi> element naming the project itself, a
               <gi>date</gi> element showing the text was added to the Collection, and an <gi>availability</gi>
               element containing a standardised statement concerning its licence.
               One or more <gi>ref</gi> elements may also follow specifying a URL from
               which the text may be downloaded. These elements must be given in the order
               specified, as shown in this example:
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <publicationStmt>
                     <distributor>COST Action ELTeC</distributor>
                     <date when="2018-11-23"/>
                     <availability>                                       
                        <licence
                           target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                           Licenced under CC-BY 4.0 </licence>
                     </availability>
                     <ref type="doi" target="10.5281/zenodo.8468"/>                                  
                      </publicationStmt>
               </egXML>
               
                  
            
            </p>

            <!--<p>This must contain a single <gi>p</gi> element containing a fixed phrase such as
                  <q>Incorporated into the ELTeC release 1.0</q> (or its equivalent in the
               appropriate language), followed by a date, tagged with the <gi>date</gi> element. </p>
            <p> Here is a simple example, for an English text : <egXML
                  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><publicationStmt>
                     <p>Incorporated into the ELTeC release 1.0 <date>2018-02-12</date></p>
                  </publicationStmt></egXML>
            </p>-->
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The source description (<gi>sourceDesc</gi>)</head>

            <p>This must contain at least one <gi>bibl</gi> element containing a bibliographic
               description of the source text from which the ELTeC version has been derived. This
               description might include any or all of the following standard TEI bibliographic
               elements: <list>
                  <item><gi>author</gi>, <gi>title</gi>, <gi>pubPlace</gi>, <gi>publisher</gi>,
                        <gi>date</gi></item>
                  <item>
                     <gi>idno</gi> may be used if the source text has a standard identifier such as
                     an ISBN or a library shelf mark</item>
                 <!-- <item>
                     <gi>relatedItem</gi> may be used to provide a description of a
                     different but related bibliographic item 
                    </item>-->
                  <item>
                     <gi>ref</gi> may be used to supply a URI if the source used is online </item>
               </list></p>
            <p>Here is a French example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><sourceDesc>
                     <bibl type="digitalSource">
                        <ref target="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k931128v"> Tatiana Leïlof
                           roman parisien (édition numerisée) </ref>
                        <publisher> gallica.bnf.fr / Bibliothèque nationale de France </publisher>
                        <idno type="ARK">12148/bpt6k931128v</idno>
                   </bibl>
               <bibl type="firstEdition"><title>Tatiana Leïlof , roman parisien, par Édouard Rod</title>
                              <publisher>E. Plon, Nourrit et Cie</publisher>
                              <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                              <date>1886</date>                          
                     </bibl>
                  </sourceDesc></egXML>
            </p>
            <p>This encoding shows that the source of the ELTeC text is the digital facsimile
               provided under the title and ARK identifier indicated, and that the first edition of
               this work was published in Paris in 1886. </p>
            <p/>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>The profile description (<gi>profileDesc</gi>)</head>

         <p>This must contain a <gi>langUsage</gi> element detailing the language or languages used
            in the text, followed optionally by a <gi>textClass</gi> element providing descriptive
            keywords, and by a mandatory <gi>textDesc</gi> element providing the sampling criteria
            applicable to this text. </p>
         <p>The <gi>textDesc</gi> element contains one of each of the following elements from the
               <ident>model.textDescPart</ident> class in the order indicated: <specList>
               <specDesc key="model.textDescPart"/>
            </specList> These elements are used to represent the sampling criteria applicable to
            the current text. They are specific to the ELTeC project, and are therefore taken from
            the ELTeC namespace (<ident>http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns</ident>) rather than the
            TEI namespace. </p>
     <p> The optional <gi>textClass</gi> element may
            contain one or more <gi>keywords</gi> elements. <!--The <gi>catRef</gi> element must have a
               <att>target</att> attribute specifying a series of classificatory codes. These codes
            are derived from the ELTeC selection criteria, and are listed here.--> Each
               <gi>keywords</gi> element may contain one or more <gi>term</gi> element describing
            some aspect of the text. At present the descriptive keywords may be freely chosen. All
            the terms in a given <gi>keywords</gi> list should use the same language, which should
            be that of the text itself, unless otherwise specified by means of an @xml:lang
            attribute. </p>
         <p> The <gi>langUsage</gi> element should contain one or more <gi>language</gi> element,
            one for each of the human languages used in the text. The @ident attribute of this
            element identifies the language using the ISO 639-2 code in the same way as the
            @xml:lang attribute. The @usage attribute may be used to indicate approximately what
            percentage of the text uses this language, or otherwise qualify it by means of a brief
            description. </p>
        
         <p> Here is an imaginary Italian example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><profileDesc>
                  <langUsage>
                     <language ident="it" usage="80"/>
                     <language ident="en" usage="10">citazioni inglesi</language>
                     <language ident="de" usage="10">citazioni tedeschi</language>
                  </langUsage>
                  <textDesc>
                     <e:authorGender key="M"/>
                     <e:canonicity key="low"/>
                     <e:size key="large"/>
                     <e:timeSlot key="T3"/>
                  </textDesc>
               </profileDesc></egXML> This text is mostly in Italian, but approximately a tenth of
            it is taken up with quotations in English, and another tenth with quotations in German.
            Its description indicates that it has a male author, is of low canonicity (i.e. few reprints have 
    been found during the period 1970-2009), contains more than 100,000
            words, and was first published between 1880 and 1899. </p>
      </div>
      <div>

         <head>The revision description (<gi>revisionDesc</gi>) </head>
         <p>This contains at least one <gi>change</gi> element, documenting significant revisions or
            versions of the asspociated text. Each change element has a @when attribute which gives
            the date of the change in W3C format (YYYY-MM-DD) and the change elements are given in
            chronological order, most recent first. The content of the element should be a brief
            sentence indicating what was done and who was responsible for doing it, using the
            language of the text. </p>
         <p> Here is an example from a Spanish text: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><revisionDesc>
                  <change when="20180427">Revisión en formato ELTeC: Lou Burnard</change>
                  <change when="20011004">Supervisión del texto : Marisa Payá (Supervisora)</change>
                  <change when="20011004">Revisión del formato : Josefina Carrión
                     (Supervisora)</change>
                  <change when="20011127">Etiquetado del texto en XML-TEI : Ana López Díaz
                     (Correctora)</change><change when="20040630">Revisión del etiquetado : Mari
                     Carmen Jerez Gaona (Correctora)</change>
               </revisionDesc>
            </egXML></p>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>

</body>
